Last year at TED I gave an introduction to the LHC.
العام الماضي في تيد أعطيتكم مقدمة عن مصادم الهدرونات الكبير
And I promised to come back and give you an update
ووعدت أن أعود وأعطيكم تقريرا بالمستجدات
on how that machine worked.
عن كيفية عمل هذه الآلة
So this is it. And for those of you that weren't there,
هذا هو. ولمن لم يكن منكم حاضرا
the LHC is the largest scientific experiment ever attempted --
مصادم الهدرونات الكبير هو أكبر تجربة علمية على الإطلاق
27 kilometers in circumference.
محيطها 27 كيلومتر
Its job is to recreate the conditions
وظيفتها هي صنع الظروف
that were present less than a billionth of a second after the universe began,
التي كانت موجودة بعد أقل من واحد من البليون من الثانية بعد بداية الكون
up to 600 million times a second.
بتردد 600 مليون مرة في الثانية
It's nothing if not ambitious.
إنه لا شيء إن لم يكن طموحا
This is the machine below Geneva.
هذه الآلة تحت جينيف
We take the pictures of those mini-Big Bangs inside detectors.
نأخذ صور لهذه الإنفجارات العظيمة المصغرة داخل مجسات
This is the one I work on. It's called the ATLAS detector --
هذا الذي أعمل عليه. يدعا بمجس أطلس
44 meters wide, 22 meters in diameter.
عرضه 44 متر، وقطره 22 متر
Spectacular picture here of ATLAS under construction
صورة مذهلة لأطلس تحت الإنشاء
so you can see the scale.
يمكنكم أن تروا الحجم
On the 10th of September last year we turned the machine on for the first time.
في 10 سبتمبر من العام الماضي أدرنا الآلة لأول مرة
And this picture was taken by ATLAS.
وأخذ أطلس هذه الصورة
It caused immense celebration in the control room.
تسبب في احتفالات هائلة في غرفة التحكم
It's a picture of the first beam particle
إنها صورة لأول جزيء شعاعي
going all the way around the LHC,
يسير على طول الطريق حول مصادم الهدرونات الكبير
colliding with a piece of the LHC deliberately,
ليستضم بجزء من مصادم الهدرونات الكبير عمدا
and showering particles into the detector.
ويغطي المجس بالجزيئات
In other words, when we saw that picture on September 10th
بصيغة أخرى، حين رأينا تلك الصورة في 10 سبتمبر
we knew the machine worked,
عرفنا أن الآلة تعمل
which is a great triumph.
وذلك انتصار كبير
I don't know whether this got the biggest cheer,
لا أعرف إن حصل هذا على أكبر تشجيع
or this, when someone went onto Google
أو هذا، حين زار أحدهم جوجل
and saw the front page was like that.
ورأى الصفحة الرئيسية كذلك
It means we made cultural impact
وهذا يعني أن لنا أثر ثقافي
as well as scientific impact.
إضافة إلى الأثر العلمي
About a week later we had a problem with the machine,
بعد أسبوع تقريبا كانت هناك مشكلة بالآلة
related actually to these bits of wire here -- these gold wires.
متعلقة بهذه الكابلات -- هذه الكابلات الذهبية
Those wires carry 13 thousand amps
هذه الكابلات تحمل 13 ألف أمبير
when the machine is working in full power.
حين تعمل الآلة على الطاقة القصوى
Now the engineers amongst you will look at them and say,
المهندسين من بينكم سينظرون إليها ويقولوا
"No they don't. They're small wires."
لا إنها لا تحملها. إنها كابلات صغيرة
They can do that because
إنها قادرة على حملها لأنها
when they are very cold they are what's called superconducting wire.
باردة جدا فتصبح فائق التوصيل
So at minus 271 degrees,
فعلى درجة سالب 271
colder than the space between the stars,
أبرد من الفضاء بين النجوم
those wires can take that current.
هذه الاسلاك الكهربائيه تستطيع حمل ذلك التيار
In one of the joints between over 9,000 magnets in LHC,
في أحد المفاصل بين أكثر من تسعة آلاف مغنطيس في مصادم الهدرونات الكبير
there was a manufacturing defect.
كان هناك عيب مصنعي
So the wire heated up slightly,
ما أدى إلى رفع حرارة الكابل قليلا
and its 13,000 amps suddenly encountered electrical resistance.
وفجأة واجهت الـ 13 ألف فولت مقاومة كهربائية
This was the result.
وكانت هذه النتيجة
Now that's more impressive
الآن هذا أكثر عجبا
when you consider those magnets weigh over 20 tons,
إذا علمتم أن المغنطيسات تزن أكثر من 20 طن
and they moved about a foot.
وقد تحركوا قرابة القدم
So we damaged about 50 of the magnets.
فأتلفنا قرابة 50 من هذه المغنطيسات
We had to take them out, which we did.
وقد اضطررنا إلى إخراجها
We reconditioned them all, fixed them.
أعدنا تهيئتهم جميعا، أصلحناهم
They're all on their way back underground now.
وجميعهم في طريقهم تحت الأرض
By the end of March the LHC will be intact again.
بنهاية مارس سيكون مصادم الهدرونات الكبير سليما مجددا
We will switch it on,
سنديره
and we expect to take data in June or July,
ونتوقع أن نجمع البيانات في يونيو أو يوليو
and continue with our quest to find out
ونستمر في بحثنا لاكتشاف
what the building blocks of the universe are.
ما هي لبنات بناء الكون
Now of course, in a way
الآن بالطبع، بطريقة ما
those accidents reignite the debate
تعيد هذه الحوادث إشعال الجدل
about the value of science and engineering at the edge. It's easy to refute.
حول قيمة العلم والهندسة على الحافة. من السهل دحضها
I think that the fact that it's so difficult,
أعتقد أنها صعبة جدا
the fact that we're overreaching, is the value of things like the LHC.
أننا نبالغ، هي قيمة أمور مثل مصادم الهدرونات الكبير
I will leave the final word to an English scientist, Humphrey Davy,
سأترك الكلمة الأخيرة لعالم إنجليزي، همفري دافي
who, I suspect,
والذي، على ما أعتقد
when defending his protege's useless experiments --
حين كان يدافع عن تجارب تلميذه الفاشلة
his protege was Michael Faraday --
كان تلميذه مايكل فاراداي
said this, "Nothing is so dangerous
قال "ما من شيء أكثر خطورة
to the progress of the human mind
على تقدم العقل البشري
than to assume that our views of science are ultimate,
من افتراض أن نظرتنا للعلم مطلقة
that there are no mysteries in nature,
أن الطبيعة لا تحمل المفاجئات
that our triumphs are complete, and that
أن انتصاراتنا اكتملت، وأنه
there are no new worlds to conquer."
لا يوجد عالم جديدة لتقهر"ـ
Thank you.
شكرا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)